Hi, it's mini teardown time. Thanks to
Andrew Perong for sending in this little
LG 800G mobile phone that he picked up
in the US. It's from a company called
TrackFone Wireless Inc. And he got this
for five US dollars delivered. Yes, it
is actually a well, I believe it's a
reconditioned unit, but it's you know,
virtually as
new here. Really, I can't tell any
difference, but it's a it's amazing. $5.
I thought we'd tear it down, have a look
what's inside a $5 phone like this. It
usually goes for about you know, $49 or
something like that, but they advertise
this thing for five bucks delivered. You
got to be kidding me. It's touch screen.
It's got a web browser in it. It does
play MP3s. It's got a SD card slot
inside.
Um And it's got Bluetooth as well
integrated. It's feature set wise,
there's virtually nothing on it. I mean,
you know, there's an SN button, return
button, end button. It's a touch screen.
It looks like you cannot actually get
into the main screen without actually
inserting a SIM. I don't have a
full-size SIM card for this thing, but
yes, it does have a 2-megapixel camera
on the back. It's going to be bare bones
and absolute crap. Comes with a tiny
little LG lithium-ion battery. It's only
900 milliamp hours, but apparently 3.4
watt hours. Apparently
like eight days standby, four hours talk
time, something like that. You know,
it's absolutely tiny. Weighs hardly
anything at all. So, I thought we'd tear
this down, see what's inside one of
these cheap ass phones. I mean, you
know, there's really not much to this at
at all. Is that an external antenna
connected there, but there you go. It's
got a full-size SIM card slot. We've got
a micro um, SD card in there and uh,
well, looks like we have a couple of
screws. Should be able to whip this part
puppy apart real quick. Now, with a real
bare-bones phone like this, it's not a
smartphone, by the way. Uh, no, I don't
think anyone would classify this as a
smartphone, even though you can run some
sort of app crappy app on it or
something like that, but it's certainly
not a uh, Android or an Apple uh,
OS, that's for sure. So, anyway, we
expect a whole lot of high level of uh,
system chip integration in this thing.
I'd be surprised if it's more than like
a three-chip uh, solution or something
like that. You know, I mean, they're
really it's going to be the main ASIC in
here, plus maybe some external memory
and you know, maybe an RF chipset and
that's probably about it. So, and of
course, it'll be a
one-board solution. The LCD on this is
not high resolution at all.
Um, and
we really
they're
really going to save every cent on their
bomb cost possible on something like
this. So, it looks like I may have to
pry this open now. There's probably some
clips in there. And by the way, there's
pretty much nothing else on the sides
here. There's a micro USB, excellent for
uh, charging. There's a power button on
the top and there's a headphone jack and
volume control, but that is it. Yeah, no
surprises for guessing that just
was all held in place by little
plastic retaining clips around the
outside. Still a bit of a mongrel, but
yeah, this is going to be
yeah, a one-board solution. Of course,
you're not going to piss money away on
uh, multiple boards, but let me I we've
got a few clips on the end there still
left. And we may
finally
have it here. Let's
uh, something's caught in that uh, top
left
corner there. No, there we go. Ah, okay.
There we go. There it is. Bang. We're in
like Flynn. And it looks like we've got
all of the magic under a can here, which
you may uh hopefully we won't have to uh
desolder that. I don't think it's uh
soldered onto the board, but there's,
you know, as we said, single board
solution uh and the crappiest
2-megapixel camera possible, I'm sure,
directly uh surface mounted onto the PCB
down there. We do have a couple of
chips. We'll try and get in there and uh
have a look at those. And we've got our
um PCB mount uh micro USB, as you'd
expect, and uh our headphone jack, and
the um SD card slots. And there's a
single-piece uh rear case with all the
various uh inserts in there for the
various contacts. Now, one thing I did
find interesting is that the little
tactile buttons on the side here for the
volume, there they are, mounted on that
little board there, the tactile buttons,
but then we've got the uh
leaf spring contacts there. You'll
notice that they've actually got uh side
contacts on the edge of the PCB like
that. And the reason I said that was
unusual because that's uh an additional
manufacturing step at the bare board PCB
level, which uh usually costs more, but,
you know, they're probably making these
things, I don't know, 100,000 of these
things, so maybe the price wasn't a huge
differentiator. I'm just surprised that
they didn't go with a
a top uh contact solution like they did
on other parts of the board over here.
It's just, you know, saves that extra
manufacturing step. And speaking of
those contacts, well, they're the ones
that actually go off to the uh
uh internal antenna, which is on the
case, which we'll have a look at in a
second, but there's the external uh
antenna contact solution for like a car
uh hands-free kit or something like
that. I'm surprised on a phone of this
little level they even bother having
that. And there are those two contacts
on the back of the case there in in
complete assembly, this big convoluted
assembly that they've got in here is
nothing but a holder essentially
for
There it is. And there's the antenna
shaped to you know form over the plastic
molding in there. And that's you know
they've gone to a reasonable amount of
trouble to do that. But once you do
actually design that it is very low cost
to implement once you get those dies
made and just stamp those things out.
And these two contacts on the board here
that looks to be like the Bluetooth
antenna. Sorry, which is another plastic
molding inside here which I'll try and
get out. And bingo there it is. If we
flip that over you can see they've done
exactly the same thing
there as what they did on the other one.
And I'm not exactly sure what we've got
there. Have we got ourselves some sort
of filter perhaps? And for those playing
along at home there's all the detail on
the internal label. And for the power
button on the top you can see that's
just another little tactile dome in
there. And I'm surprised that they've
actually
sprung for the extra little flat flex
cable going over to the main board like
that.
They're pissing away half a cent there
in the manufacturing cost. Maybe could
have optimized that one out if they
tried a bit harder. And I flipped the
board out here just near the power
tactile button and you can see these
four contacts on the bottom here. They
actually go down
inside the unit down in here and you can
see that that's obviously the flat flex
membrane going in there and driving the
back light for the screen. So that was
just a cheap and easy way to press fit
connect the board and get that down onto
the
LCD down in there. But the main
connection to the LCD of course is your
more traditional flat flex connector up
on here which then just pops right on
over like that. And that's the daughter
we've got on the LCD flat flex and
the only number we've got on the LCD is
that one and I can't find any info on
that at all. So, the type, I don't know.
If anyone's got any info on the LCD,
please leave it in the comments. And
underneath this plastic
section on top here, that's just our
vibration motor there and we just have
our speaker and another little chip
hidden under there. Because there's
absolutely nothing on the back side of
this board except they have done a
double-sided load and clearly that's
just a little headphone driver amp
there. And some more cheap ass just
little tactile domes directly mounted on
the board there for the buttons on the
front of the case. And of course, you're
not going to you know, get any more than
that cuz these tactile domes, they're
ridiculously cheap. They you can get
them pick and place soldered directly on
the board or you can just put them like
individually pick and place or you can
get them
you know, as a complete sheet or
something like that that sticks over.
Very cheap manufacturing process and it
works just fine. There's nothing wrong
with it whatsoever. Some of these
tactile domes, depends on the
manufacturer, can have incredibly long
operating lives. And it looks like we
can just pop off this metal can on the
top with these tabs here. Easy peasy.
And we've got a few chips more than what
I was expecting, but you know, not too
much out of the ballpark really. We've
got ourselves a backup battery there.
We'll take the label off there to see
exactly what we've got. And they've got
Is that a heat
pad? Yeah, that could be a heat sinker.
Yep. Pad on the top of there
that actually connects through to the
metal case. So, let's take a look in
more detail. And this is where all the
magic happens. This is the main system
on chip I see. It's an Infineon X-Gold
213 and this contains
everything including the kitchen sink, I
think. Let's go to the data sheet. And
here it is, the Infineon X-Gold 213,
lowest cost edge single chip solution
for mobile internet browsing and
messaging. It's the first single chip 65
nanometer process CMOS technology that
integrates baseband RF transceiver,
power management unit, and FM radio.
After successful market introduction,
the second generation X-Gold 101,
formerly the E-Gold, uh the 213 now
takes a next step towards bringing new
features into low-cost segment. That's
what we got here. Thereby setting new
industry standards in system on chip.
And this is how they get the price
point. It's got an integrated FM radio,
high-performance arm processor, edge
functionality, uh that enables uh web
browsing, music and video, camera, FM
broadcasting, messaging, all sorts of
stuff. Due to the single chip
integration, this functionality can be
realized in a very small PCB area giving
the handset manufacturer
highest design flexibility. In this
case, doesn't really matter. They really
had plenty of room in this side in
inside this phone in the scheme of
things. But uh this, you know, look at
the main features. Direct conversion
receiver, fully integrated digital
control, RF synthesizer including delta
sigma transmitter, FM radio, stereo
recording, quarter VGA screen, 256 uh
262 colors. So, it displays that. Uh
handles all the display directly, all in
the one chip. Up to 3 megapixel camera.
We've only got uh 2 megapixel here.
That's 8-bit parallel interface. Um
direct SIM support, UST uh USB 2.0 goes
directly in, memory card interface,
Bluetooth, AGPS, WLAN. Uh and it's got
the power management. I told you it had
the kitchen sink. It's all in there.
Class D audio amp, um stereo headset
without uh coupling. Then And not sure
what that extra chip near the uh
external headphone was. Maybe it's a
microphone amp coming back in perhaps.
That might explain it a bit better.
DC to DC converter for the backlight.
Handles all the charging, everything
else. And it handles a JPEG encoding and
MPEG playback and the whole shebang. I
mean, fantastic. And it's a point pain
in the ass 0.5 mm pitch
BGA device. Requires they even tell you
it requires a six layer minimum PCB just
to route the thing out. So, there you
go. You can't just get this on a four
layer board. Most likely not unless you
can pull a few tricks. But there you go.
Here's the internal block diagram for
the thing. And well, as you can see,
yeah, I can probably see the kitchen
sink in there somewhere as well. It's
got even secure ROM and e-fuse and all
sorts of things. Handles the keypad and
man, I what I didn't see here is a touch
screen controller. I didn't mention see
mention of that. So, we might need an
external
uh
touch screen controller perhaps. Um
maybe that's the Look, over here next to
our transmitter we've got our saw filter
over saw filter block external. So,
maybe that's what we that's what was
inside that cam we saw over here. But
look at this. It drives the vibration
motor directly. Handles all the
lithium ion lithium polymer charging,
everything else. It's got the microphone
inputs direct. Uh
fantastic. Another tiny little BGA
device down in there. Lots of caps
hanging off it. Not exactly sure what
that one's doing at all. Likewise for
that one there. What is it? KSRBR?
No idea. And of course, there's all the
external inductors and caps around there
as part of the power management
circuitry for that thing that was inside
it. We've got external crystal out here.
And uh
what else we got? Looks like we've
possibly got another uh oscillator
module there. I can't quite make out
that number on there, but uh clearly we
have an Intel uh memory device right
next to the main system-on-chip. And
isn't it always remarkable how this has
the kitchen sink on it, this incredible
system-on-chip device, and the memory's
bigger. And you'll notice that they've
actually gunked up all around the chips
around there. Why they've done that uh
could be for moisture ingress uh reasons
maybe if it's a uh hard type to stop any
uh thermal expansion issues with the
main BGA devices there just for a bit of
reliability. And there's our transmit
module there. It's an uh RF Micro
Devices RF 7161
to the data sheet. And here it is,
transmit module. It's a quad band, does
GSM 850 uh edge uh 900 and 1800 as well.
And it's not a huge amount in there.
Just got a main uh power amplifier here
and some filtering, some switching, and
basically goes out to the antenna. Some
built-in ESD protection in there, which
is quite nice. But there you go, that's
just a
a uh complete transmit solution for a
GSM phone. And it also contains uh
four receive ports as well. And here you
go, it's got PHEMT switch technology.
That, if you don't know, is a stands for
HEMT is high electron mobility
transistor. Wikipedia, that one. And of
course that system-on-chip was lacking
one thing, and that was the Bluetooth
capability, which is handled here by
this uh Broadcom BCM2070.
And that's a Bluetooth uh 3.0 compatible
module. So, that's all there is to it.
But that's extra cost in this sort of
phone. So, you can see that the this
exact same model without Bluetooth
capability, well, I don't know how much
they're paying for that chip. You know,
what 50 cents in volume? I don't know.
You can shave that cost off. That's a
you know, a fairly substantial part of
your bomb cost when you've only got, you
know, like four major devices here and
and sort of you know, a few
miscellaneous jelly bean stuff around
here. It all adds up. One of these
devices could be the touch screen
controller cuz that's not built into the
main SOC. So, I don't know. I can't make
out those devices, but we've got a few
jelly bean stuff around here. Some of
them are part of the camera module down
here, but yeah, nothing much doing. So,
there you go. I hope you enjoyed a brief
look inside that LG 800G
bare bones mobile phone. Bottom of the
range phone which Andrew got for $5
delivered.
Crazy from Tech Phone. Sure, it's a
refurbished model, but unbelievable what
you can get for the price these days.
And big single on chip solution. You can
see how they got the price down.
Although, this one is of course, you
know, built up to a bit of a spec with
the extra Bluetooth chipset. Woohoo! You
know, you can probably get chipsets now
which integrate the transmit
functionality in there as well. Almost
getting Sorry, almost getting down to
like a single chip solution these days
perhaps. But, basically, this is if you
ignore the Bluetooth functionality, for
example, it's almost a two chip solution
there really. Yeah, there might be an
external touch screen screen controller
and a couple of other miscellaneous glue
stuff, but really no big deal. And
that's how they get the price down on
these things. It all comes down to that
bomb cost in the end and how much they
can, you know, shave the cost off that
and shave the cost off in manufacture.
So, I'm not sure exactly how many of
these suckers they would have, Uh, you
know, tooled up for in production, but
you know, could have been like a hundred
thousand or something like that. They
probably wouldn't even get out of bed to
manufacture less than a hundred thousand
uh, of one particular type of phone. So,
this isn't uh, quite as bare-bones as
you can get because they didn't have to
include the Bluetooth, they didn't have
to include the micro SD card, they
didn't have to include uh, the camera
and other stuff and their headphones and
stuff like that. If they just wanted,
well, shock horror, a phone that just
actually made and received calls, they
could have got the
uh, you know, that bomb cost down even
further. But, as you can see, there's
bugger all in these things. And if you
can com- compare them with phones of,
you know, even ten years ago, the
system-on-chip integration these days is
absolutely incredible. So, there you go.
If you want to discuss that, jump on
over to the EV blog forum, that's the
best place to do it. Or, you can always
leave it YouTube comments, of course.
And thank you very much, Andrew, for
sending that one in, spending the
whopping five bucks
to get this thing including postage. I
think it cost more to send it to me here
in Australia than it did for him to buy
it and get it shipped to him in the US.
I mean, that's just it's crazy. What
sort of world are we living in? I don't
know.
Catch you next time.